<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Aindien&#x27;s Computer Guides</title>
    <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien" />
    <updated>2019-11-28T16:22:13-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Jason Moore</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien</id>

    <entry>
        <title>What Cloud Computing Really Means</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/what-cloud-computing-really-means.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/what-cloud-computing-really-means.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:38-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/30/cloud-computing.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p>Cloud computing is used a lot these days. Many times people are referring to totally different concepts. When mentioning it, however, there is definitely a disconnect or a lack of understanding of what this means. I will clear some things up and give a good overview of what we are talking about when we say "cloud computing".</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/30/cloud-computing.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Cloud computing is used a lot these days. Many times people are referring to totally different concepts. When mentioning it, however, there is definitely a disconnect or a lack of understanding of what this means. I will clear some things up and give a good overview of what we are talking about when we say "cloud computing".</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Introduction</strong></h2>
<p>Cloud computing really boils down to a few different concepts and their variations. These few concepts are usually cloud servers that end up running services for businesses or home users. For example, you can pay a monthly fee for a cloud server and install whatever you want on it. Many people will install an operating system on it and run apps that do whatever you need. The differences in these cloud systems are how much the user has to maintain. Lets get into some specifics.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Software As A Service</strong></h2>
<p>A user will consume a service which is often through a web interface. This is a very popular method of delivery because everyone can use a browser. Examples that are often hosted on a cloud server are email, inventory systems, pbx's, and documentation apps. The user of these apps do not control anything and just use the software they need. There is often a subscription in place that customers will have to pay for in order to use some software. Everything is hosted by the people that sell the subscription. This <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_as_a_service">software as a service</a> has been around a long time as it can be traced back to the 60's-70's era. As our technology has advanced and computers have become more ubiquitous, cloud computing has become more popular.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Platform As A Service</strong></h2>
<p>This model of cloud consumption allows users to install apps or services onto the hardware and control its <a href="http://www.aindien.com/networking-basics-physical-topologies/">network topology</a> to some degree. This could be something that is created by the user, bought through a third party, or something open source and free that was downloaded. Linux is a popular example here as it is usually installed onto cloud hardware. From there you can host a web server or a database. The user will have control over the application or software he installs but none of the hardware. Developers have this space in the cloud to create their applications for business or personal use. It was a huge factor in the increase of developer careers.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Infrastructure As A Service</strong></h2>
<p>This cloud computing model is where the user has the most control. They can install software and configure it. Storage and networking components are also configurable by the user. They still do not control any of the physical <a href="http://www.aindien.com/computer-networking-networking-hardware/">hardware</a> because that will be in a remote location most likely. One of the great things about this model is that it can scale quickly, up or down. If you write an app that becomes very popular overnight, you can add more resources in just a few minutes in order to maintain functionality for your customers.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Private Cloud</strong></h2>
<p>The hardware that provides cloud computing to a specific business unit is often considered a Private cloud. This is one or more servers that provide services in one of the categories I talked about above. This <a href="https://www.liquidweb.com/kb/difference-private-cloud-premise/">Private cloud</a> can provide<a href="http://www.aindien.com/networking-basics-applications-network-devices/"> apps</a> and services. The hardware can be located on site of your organization or at another location. This is a more secure solution than having your data sit on the internet somewhere as more effort is needed to keep it safe. It can be done but if you have the option this is often the best way.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Public Cloud</strong></h2>
<p>This is another stack of hardware except it is available for public use. There will be systems and processes set up to allow public consumption of certain services. Email falls into this category as anyone can sign up for a cloud or hosted solution. Once you sign up you can start getting email. So, a third party person or business can offer their computing power for a subscription. Their platform is open to all and anyone can sign up to use these resources. A public cloud is a good way for business to save money as they will not have to purchase the hardware.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Hybrid Cloud</strong></h2>
<p>As you can imagine this is a combination of the previous types of Cloud we have discussed. However, to be a hybrid cloud computing model it must allow app to be portable between the different services. It is most often a mix of private and public models. The applications hosted here are almost always shared. Businesses only pay for the resources they need which is great for both parties.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Virtualization</strong></h2>
<p>Ah virtualization, one of my favorite topics. I could write and write about this. It is ever changing and just as important. It is what makes cloud computing possible. When you virtualize, you can do it two different ways. The first way is from within an operating system and this is called a type 2 hypervisor. This type 2 hypervisor is reliant on the operating system. The other way to virtualize is outside of the operating system which is on the host hardware itself. Other named include bare metal and type 1. Type 1 is superior to type 2 because of performance, reliability, and features. The drawback is that it takes more knowledge. The host is where a hypervisor runs and the resultant virtual machines you create are called guests.</p>
<p>Virtualization allows you to use your system's resources very efficiently. You can actually get close to to using it all without performance degradation.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Software Defined Networking</strong></h2>
<p>Everything we have talked about is software based. Software defined <a href="http://www.aindien.com/aindiens-guide-to-network-communications/">networking</a> is no exception. This software controls every aspect of your network and to a greater degree than would be possible otherwise. Understand that the whole reason you use software defined networking is to make your network more efficient. This happens by grouping same network functions into some software which makes it easier, quicker, and less error prone to complete.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Storage Area Networks</strong></h2>
<p>All computers, services, and clouds need storage. A storage area network is, in simple terms, a network of storage devices. They are considerably expensive and can be hard to maintain. Lets be more precise, however. It is typically high speed storage because you want as little latency as possible. Storage area networks provide block level storage for it to be available to the systems that need it. The end user will see it as locally attached storage. They will increase your storage speed and application performance if they rely on storage. Fibre channel is used because of its speed.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>iSCSI</strong></h2>
<p>SCSI <a href="http://www.aindien.com/computer-networking-devices/">devices</a> have been around a long time. I built a computer a long time ago with chained SCSI hard drives together. It was a great technology then and it still is now. Since it has just evolved, iSCSI is the language of storage and is how storage technology communicates with other similar devices. ISCSI stands for internet small computer systems interface. It is a storage protocol that works in conjunction with TCP/IP. <a href="http://www.aindien.com/how-to-make-the-jump-to-system-administrator/">Administrators</a> use it to connect computing devices to network storage. You can use it with a San, Nas and any type of hard drive.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Attached Storage</strong></h2>
<p>Cloud computing storage does not get more simple than this. If a storage area network is out of your budget then buy or build <a href="http://www.aindien.com/network-basics-easy-addressing-and-routing/">network attached storage</a>. This can be a simple unit that is bought or it can be an old computer set up for storage with a relevant operating system. Network attached storage is a file level storage model. Networking it will get the most functionality out of it and will support many devices. You will buy a Nas with a certain amount of storage but increasing storage is as easy as adding a larger drive. A Nas is easy to set up because it will not have a full fledged operating system installed.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How To Construct Loops in C++</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/how-to-construct-loops-in-c.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/how-to-construct-loops-in-c.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:38-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/loops-in-c-0.png" alt="" />
                    <p>Today's guide will be over loops in C++. I have been wanting to get to my latest C++ article for a while. So lets break out our favorite text editor and compiler and have some real fun today!</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/loops-in-c-0.png" alt="" />
                <p>Today's guide will be over loops in C++. I have been wanting to get to my latest C++ article for a while. So lets break out our favorite text editor and compiler and have some real fun today!</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Loops in C++</strong></h2>
<p>Loops in c++ will generally require some specific operators. These are simple and easy to memorize. They also use variables which can use <a href="http://www.aindien.com/beginning-c-input-output-basics/">inputs and outputs</a>. The loops are used for mathematical expressions, testing, and <a href="http://www.aindien.com/how-to-read-data-from-a-file-with-c/">reading from files</a>. Creative uses abound, however, and you should indulge yourself whenever you think of a new use. So once you get the hang of things try and experiment some. Your usage and skills will grow the more you do that.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Types of Loops</strong></h2>
<p>There are a few different kinds of loops. Looping in C++ will require you to be proficient in all of them. Examples include while loops, the do-while loops and for loops. These loops are used in different scenarios. The one you choose will depend on your situation. When you get more experience it will be easier to recognize when to use each type of loop. For example you can even use them when you <a href="http://www.aindien.com/beginning-c-making-decisions/">make decisions</a>.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Incrementing and Decrementing Values</strong></h2>
<p>When you are looping in c++ you will have to modify variables and their values often. Increasing a value is called incrementing. Decreasing a value is called decrementing.</p>
<p>The increment symbol is [     ++     ]. The decrement symbol is [     --     ]. They should not be too hard to memorize.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Incrementing Example</strong></h2>
<p>This is a short example of incrementing a variable.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-880 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/looping-in-c-1.png" alt="loops in c++" width="656" height="342" /> loops in c++</p>
<p>This is an example of a post-increment variable. That means the variable was read first and then incremented. You can also increment the variable first and then read the variable in to memory. If you want to do that, put ++ before the variable name. Nice and simple!</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>The While Loop</strong></h2>
<p>This is the standard first loop that you usually see. It is simple and has a lot of uses. A loop is a construct that helps you repeat actions. For example, if you have a text file that has 5,000 computer names in it, all on a separate line, you can use a loop to look at each line. Now it might not make sense why you would want to do that but you could sort these items, see how many started with a certain letter, or look for certain names within each line. The point is, it is much quicker to use a loop to do this than have a person look at each line individually.</p>
<p>A while loop is made of two main parts. They are the expression that is tested and the statement that is carried out if the test is successful. The expression must be evaluated to be true or false. This is called a boolean. Now the statement, which is executed, is any c++ statement that can be carried out.</p>
<p>What happens is the expression is tested. If it is true the loop continues to the statement block. It is then executed until the expression is false. This is what makes it a pre-test loop. That means its condition is tested before the loop takes place. A loop is always constructed so that it becomes false at some point. It is bad form to make loops that never become false by the way, so don't do this. Your program also will not work right if a loop never becomes false. This is a standard way to construct loops in c++.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Example While Loops</strong></h2>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Lets go to an example now.</p>
<p>https://gist.github.com/jahlelin/be697086e0c1a725b4c1418625dd5f3c</p>
<p>This is just  basic while loop. I asked the loop to print to screen the numbers from 1 to 20. The (num &lt; 21) ensures that the loop does not go past 20. As you can see in the loop, I also asked the variable (num) to increment by +1 each time the loop executed. There isn't much more to it than that. Here is what the output looks like.</p>
<p><img class="size-large wp-image-908" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/Screenshot-from-2019-07-20-15-30-49-1024x356.png" alt="loops in c++" width="1024" height="356" /> loops in c++</p>
<p>Lets do another example where we decrement a variable after each loop execution.</p>
<p>https://gist.github.com/jahlelin/5260d78249a25a8d5e3b36123994e4a8</p>
<p>In this short example I just decrement the variable (num) from 25 to 15.  During the loop I decreased the value of the variable by 1. That is called decrementing. Let me show the output below so you can see.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-909" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/loops-in-c-2-1024x245.png" alt="loops in c++ 2" width="1024" height="245" /></p>
<p>There, that is nice and easy.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Variable Counters</strong></h2>
<p>Counters go hand in hand with loops. The reason is that sometimes we want to know how many iterations a loop has gone through. Another scenario is that sometimes we want a loop to only run a certain number of times. That is why counters are important. They are just variables that are incremented or decremented when a loop executes. You will see I use them to control the loops I use.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Do-While Loop</strong></h2>
<p>A do-while loop is the opposite of a while loop. What I mean by this is that its statement is done before its condition is tested. This makes it a post-test loop. This loop will always make one iteration because of this. So when you are writing a function or whole program, if you need your loop to execute at least once then use a do-while loop. A unique part of this loop is that it always ends with a semicolon, which makes it different than a straight while loop. That makes it confusing to people first learning too. Lets look at an example.</p>
<p>https://gist.github.com/jahlelin/5880f5f628d6c23861b9af9a9339b741</p>
<p>Everything looks mostly the same except the format of the loop. That would be correct too. This is how a do_while loop works and it is also a simple way to construct loops in c++. In this loop you can see we take an action first and then evaluate whether our condition is true. I then increment the variable in the loop. The loop then repeats as long as our condition is true. Here is the output for this very simple loop if anyone is curious.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-912" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/loops-in-c-3-1024x151.png" alt="loops in c++ 3" width="1024" height="151" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>The For Loop</strong></h2>
<p>When you know the exact number of times a loop should execute then a for loop is an even better choice. A for loop will initialize a counter to its starting value. It will test the counter to its max value. Finally it will update the counter after each iteration of the loop. It is a pre-test loop which means it does its comparisons before going through the rest of the loop. You should use a for loop whenever you need a variable  initialized or know how many times you want the loop to run.</p>
<p>There are several tricks you can do with for loops. You can update the counter directly to better control your loop. Going forward or backward is no problem of course. Defining and initializing your main variable in the loop is often a good idea. So lets try one of these out.</p>
<p>https://gist.github.com/jahlelin/6597f8efac0361556450f4f068401ebf</p>
<p>So this one is slightly different. The initialization, condition, and updtate of the variable is done on all one line. You then just have whatever valid c++ statement down below. Here is the resulting output when I compiled and ran it.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-913" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/29/loops-in-c-4-1024x238.png" alt="loops in c++ 4" width="1024" height="238" /></p>
<p>So nice and simple.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Working With Accumulators</strong></h2>
<p>An accumulator is the sum of numbers every time a <a href="https://www.w3schools.in/cplusplus-tutorial/loops/for/">loop</a> iterates. This is very common in loops and is important when constructing loops in c++. This could be sales totals, number of laps in a race, or how many cards you have discarded in a game of pokemon. Its important. In each iteration of the loop the accumulator will contain the total from the numbers read by the loop.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>
<p>Loops in c++ have many uses. They are used constantly but at a more complicated level of course. You can evaluate thousands or millions of numbers or letters in an instant. Much can be done when you can look at that much data quickly. Constructing loops in c++ is easy, you just have to figure out which loop you want to work with. Some people use all of them but others will try and use one loop as much as possible. Either can work but ultimately you want to do what will make your program work the best.</p>
<p>I hope you enjoyed this article. If you did please share it on your social media because I will be writing more. Have a great day!</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Network Management Guide</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/network-management-guide.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/network-management-guide.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:38-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/28/network-management-0.png" alt="" />
                    <p>In this network management guide I try to talk about the basics of everything that goes into managing and monitoring a network. I will talk about monitoring most aspects of you network along with things to do to help it.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/28/network-management-0.png" alt="" />
                <p>In this network management guide I try to talk about the basics of everything that goes into managing and monitoring a network. I will talk about monitoring most aspects of you network along with things to do to help it.</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Management</strong></h2>
<p>In <a href="http://aindien.com/networking-basics-physical-topologies/">network</a> management there are many details to keep track of. Monitoring is a huge task but it is one that needs to be done thoroughly. There are many ways to do it and tools to use. This guide talks about many of the requirements that you will need to monitor.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Monitoring Tools</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-873 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/28/network-management-2.png" alt="network management" width="786" height="450" /> network management</p>
<p>A packet or protocol analyzer is one of the first tools that we can use to examine a network. They can display, capture, and save packets. This software can read packets intended for other devices. If it is used in promiscuous mode then the packet sniffer is seeing the information pass across a network.</p>
<p>One of the most popular example of protocol analyzers is called <a href="https://www.wireshark.org/">Wireshark</a>. It is very popular because it is free and works quite well. It can specify which network interface is to capture packets. You can operate it in promiscuous mode to see all traffic. The software can define what types of packets are to be captured. Finally, you can tell Wireshark how long a packet capture should run before it terminates the connection.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Scanning Tools</strong></h2>
<p>A port scanner is another type of tool to look at a <a href="http://aindien.com/computer-networking-networking-hardware/">network</a>. They can examine specific machines to check for open ports. If you see a port scan hitting your server then it often means that someone will try to attack your network. The person that is doing that is trying to find open ports on your machine. If he can do that then he will then see if you have anything vulnerable.</p>
<p>When analyzing your own network you need to see what machines are generating the most traffic. This will often be a clue as to what machines are compromised if the traffic is a lot more than usual. However, you will have to do this over a period of time to establish a baseline for traffic so that you know what is out of the ordinary.</p>
<p>Packet flow monitoring gives an overview of the traffic. A flow is the network traffic between two different machines. We want to use this monitoring because it gives us a good idea of the usage on parts of out network.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>SNMP Network Management</strong></h2>
<p>This is simple <a href="http://aindien.com/networking-basics-applications-network-devices/">network</a> management protocol. It is used for network management and it is very useful. It is the standard for <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-use-the-computer-management-tools-in-windows-10/">management</a> and it is very popular. SNMP agents are put on all your machines you want to monitor. This application tool will then occasionally ask the agents on those machines whether everything is working as intended or not. You can configure your application to ask once a minute or once every hour. It will be up to you to decide what is best for your environment.</p>
<p>Common devices that need monitoring are routers, switches, and servers. Keep in mind that you need actual enterprise network gear to has these capabilities. You can not go to your local office store and get a router there that will be able to do this.</p>
<p>Since we know that the management software can ask the agents for information we will need to display that information in a nice way. Messaging can be configured to give us the information that we need.</p>
<p>There are a few different versions of SNMP so use the most current if possible for security purposes.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>System Logging</strong></h2>
<p>All modern operating systems have system logging included. We need this on our servers so that we can go back and look at these logs to see what is happening. These can be generic operating system logs, database logs, or various application logs. It is important to look at them occasionally to make sure nothing is different or weird in your systems. However, they are a great place to start when diagnosing problems.</p>
<p>They can be very resource intensive so monitor that when you can. We use these to see what is happening on any given day or minute of a day.</p>
<p>SYSLOG is important to know about. It is a standard for logging and reporting. It has error codes from 0-7 with 0 being the worst and classified as an emergency. The SYSLOG software functions as a server. This is nice because applications can send their local logs to this remote server. It will collect and make things easy to analyze.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-868 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/28/network-management-1.png" alt="network management" width="887" height="339" /> network management</p>
<p>Monitoring alerts can be sent to anyone that requires it. SMS messaging is often chosen and convenient. This allows administrators to be on call and responsible for their systems.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Environment Monitoring</strong></h2>
<p>Conditions need to be monitored in your network closets and server rooms. The rooms do not need to be too hot, cold, or humid. So we need to keep them within a safe operating range. These locations should be monitored for temperature and humidity. The solution tot his is to add sensors that connect to our network. These <a href="http://www.apc.com/shop/us/en/products/APC-Temperature-Humidity-Sensor/P-AP9335TH">sensors</a> should have SNMP and alerts so they can tell the administrator when something is wrong.</p>
<p>Power is another thing that should be monitored. The UPS's should have SNMP as well ti send out alerts if power is failing or conditions that are bad. UPS's can also provide limited power for servers so they can be shut down normally. However, this only works if we know that power conditions are bad so getting that first alert nice and quick is what matters here.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Wireless Surveying Tools</strong></h2>
<p>Another topic that is important these days is WiFi interference. We all have several devices that operate with WiFi that we need to know how to help our signal and make sure that our equipment is operating correctly.</p>
<p>Your work space should be monitored to make sure your wireless signals are getting to all the places they need to. The signals should be strong so users can do what they need to do. It is helpful to make a map for reference using an online drawing tool. Label where the signal is good and also where it is bad. Elevators and other metal structures are always bad for wireless signals. They can not get through metal so people on the other side could have bad reception.</p>
<p>There are specialized tools that can help us take a site survey. These tools can be software or they can be hand held devices that many vendors make. These are called wireless analyzers. They are used for troubleshooting insecure networks, connectivity, and doing reports on a network.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Getting A Baseline For Network</strong></h2>
<p>When we are baselining a <a href="http://aindien.com/how-the-osi-model-works/">network</a> that means we are getting its normal behavior. We want to see the usual traffic and issues on an average day. That way we know when something is out of the ordinary. This should include knowing our hardware resource utilization of devices like our workstations and laptops. Knowing the bandwidth that our devices use is also very important.</p>
<p>When taking a baseline you should do them at different times of the day. This means that you should measure activity on when the network is slow and also when it should be busy.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Telemetry Logging</strong></h2>
<p>Every operating system has different telemetry tools available. It is important to use these often know what is happening on key machines. You can analyze traffic going in and out. Seeing what spikes your <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-protect-yourself-from-ransomware/">network traffic</a> is also important.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Analyzing Network Utilization</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-874 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/28/network-management-3.png" alt="network management" width="1057" height="429" /> network management</p>
<p>While we always hope our traffic is moving quickly we sometimes get bottlenecks. It is a component with a lower capacity than the rest of the system. It is what is holding the rest of the system from going faster. In a machine it is often the hard drive that is the slowest part of the system for example. That is a bottleneck.</p>
<p>Bandwidth usage is important for our WAN connections. WAN is of course our wide area network. When WAN traffic is unusually slow we may have configurations issues at our router or gateway.</p>
<p>We should also monitor our storage. SAN's are a popular type of storage for enterprises. A SAN is a storage area network. Tracking the usage of our storage is very important to ensure users have what they need.</p>
<p>CPU and memory usage are other attributes that should be monitored. If there are bottlenecks in any of these areas then we may need to upgrade certain devices or components.</p>
<p>As mentioned above, analyzing our wireless is also a good idea. Most traffic is on the 2.4 GHz section instead of the 5.0 GHz spectrum. There are many channels that can overlap and cause issues if they become too crowded.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Analyzing Network Interface Data</strong></h2>
<p>Monitoring interfaces for their link status is helpful. This is communicated back and forth to your software. You can also look at the devices to see the status. For example, printers and workstations have network cards in the back with lights on them to indicate status. This is helpful when troubleshooting issues. SNMP enabled devices will also report when a link is down.</p>
<p>Device and workstation interfaces can be monitored for more than its link status. Over time, errors and dropped packets can mean you have a more serious issue. High usage over time can mean you have driver or software issues.</p>
<p>The interface speed on a device must match the device it is connected to. However, most ethernet devices support a range of speeds and will go back to the speed where everything works.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Configuration Backups</strong></h2>
<p>As your network grows it is important to save the configuration of your devices. This is very helpful when moving them around or replacing them. Most devices can backup their configurations using TFTP or trivial file transfer protocol. After backing up all your data you need to protect those files. This is called data archiving. It is the storage of data securely off for long periods of time. This data archive should be at another location.</p>
<p>If a natural disaster happens like a tornado then network devices can be brought back to their original state.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Managing Configuration Baselines</strong></h2>
<p>Configuration baselines specify a functional state for a device. Baselines are useful in configuration management to establish a configuration state and define a change in configuration. Baselines can be used in auditing to confirm configuration status.</p>
<p>Server machines can be configured to automatically get updates to reach a baseline level. Data center management software can automatically take servers offline, fix any issues, and then bring them back online. If a device does not meet pre-defined standards then it must be brought to the level where it does. This process can be automate depending on the device and software.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Mobile Device Management</strong></h2>
<p>Smart phones and tablets are being used more and more in the workplace. You need a way to manage all these devices when they attach to your network. People are using these devices because they are easy to use and very portable. I use my smart phone for tracking work orders and many other things when I am not at my desk. They are very useful indeed.</p>
<p>Exchange server can be used to communicate with our phones to give us our corporate email and calendars.  Our management software needs to be able to remote wipe devices that might be lost or stolen. This protects our network. Devices should also support encryption.</p>
<p>Mobile devices all need to connect wirelessly. That means our network needs to provide proper signal everywhere its expected. Businesses often incorporate a guest wireless network for this reason.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Access Control</strong></h2>
<p>A NAC is a network access control. It is a method of ensuring connecting devices meet our network policy. When machines or mobile devices connect to our network we can make sure that it meets certain standards.</p>
<p>A network access control will usually check for antivirus, operating system updates, and make sure the firewall is enabled. NAC's will quarantine systems if they do not meet certain standards.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Documenting Your Network</strong></h2>
<p><img class="wp-image-875 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/28/network-management-4.png" alt="network management" width="999" height="418" /> network management</p>
<p>Documentation is always important. You should document everything you can. Network configuration is especially vital. Configurations of your firewalls and <a href="http://aindien.com/network-basics-easy-addressing-and-routing/">switches</a> should always be done. You should document your server and cable closets. Labeling cables that go into switches is also very useful.</p>
<p>Documenting your IP's is something every network admin should do. This lets you now what is happening and lets you know how to access everything on your network.</p>
<p>Assets should be documented too. Every significant device needs to be on a list somewhere to keep track of what you have. This will let you see if everything has the same patches and operating system.</p>
<p>Asset management software should include ID's, locations, and software versions.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Industrial Networks</strong></h2>
<p>An ICS is an industrial control system. They control industrial systems that are in warehouses or plants. You also see them in energy, power, and water plants. They are often networked but do not provide access to the outside internet.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Private Networks</strong></h2>
<p>A common plan for security is to use private addresses on your lan. Everyone does this now and it is common practice. The reason why this helps is that these private addresses are not directly accessible from the internet.</p>
<p>Security for your network should have many layers. <a href="http://aindien.com/computer-networking-devices/">Firewalls</a> should be there too obviously. They will filter traffic that comes in. Firewalls should be host based and at the endpoints to cover everything.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Reducing Network Congestion</strong></h2>
<p>One way to help with congested <a href="http://aindien.com/aindiens-guide-to-network-communications/">network traffic</a> is to segment different parts of your network from the rest of it. For example, if a particular device or server uses a lot of bandwidth then it could be moved over to a separate network segment so that it does not interfere with the rest of the network traffic.</p>
<p>Load balancing can also help with network traffic. This is useful when you have tons of network traffic. I can be used to split loads between servers to help  with congestion.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>
<p>There are many things to consider for network management. You have monitoring of a lot of different aspects. There is security to consider. Making your users happy with the right level of performance is also a necessary consideration.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Powershell For Beginners</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/powershell-for-beginners.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/powershell-for-beginners.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-0.png" alt="" />
                    <p>My Powershell for beginners guide will teach you the fundamentals of this tool in a Windows environment. It has been around a long time and has been through several versions already. Many information technology people have waited to become familiar with this tool. They did so because many were not sure it would continue to be supported in the future. Well we now know that not only has it continued to be supported but it is the preferred way by many to administer a Windows environment. So continue with me and we will discuss the basics so that you can go on and make this a long learning endeavor.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-0.png" alt="" />
                <p>My Powershell for beginners guide will teach you the fundamentals of this tool in a Windows environment. It has been around a long time and has been through several versions already. Many information technology people have waited to become familiar with this tool. They did so because many were not sure it would continue to be supported in the future. Well we now know that not only has it continued to be supported but it is the preferred way by many to administer a Windows environment. So continue with me and we will discuss the basics so that you can go on and make this a long learning endeavor.</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Powershell For Beginners</strong></h2>
<p>Powershell is a command oriented scripting environment. This means that you can open up a console and run a series of commands to accomplish various tasks. It also means that you can run a series of commands as a script over and over. Scripting is very important for your environment as it lets you automate certain tasks over and over.</p>
<p>If you work in <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-make-the-jump-to-system-administrator/">information technology</a> then you need to start learning this as soon as possible. There is much you can do with it and there will be even more you can do with it in the future. It will help you earn more money in your career too. Who can really argue with that?</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Using The Help System</strong></h2>
<p>So you have convinced yourself to start learning Powershell for beginners. Now what? The single best piece piece of advice I can give is to learn the help system. Let me give you a short example. I was asked the other day to do something. I had no idea at the time how to do it. So I went to my desk and opened up the console and started the help system. From a console it is [get-help] and looks like this.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-833 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/powershell-for-beginners-1.png" alt="powershell for beginners 1" width="1090" height="182" /></p>
<p>I had a slight idea of what command I would need and looked at the help options for it. I was actually wrong the first time so then tried another option which would work eventually. The important thing to learn here is that using the help system allows you to see the options and arguments with helpful descriptions to see if a command might work for you.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-834 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-for-Beginners-2.png" alt="Powershell for Beginners 2" width="1086" height="255" /></p>
<p>I wanted to import a third party module and the help showed me how to do it.</p>
<p>To start lets make sure you have the current version of help so you have all of its benefits. Type the command in yellow at your prompt.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-835 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-3.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 3" width="1087" height="179" /></p>
<p>The help system will even give examples. This is especially handy like when your totally unfamiliar with a command. Below is an example.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-836 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-4.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 4" width="1077" height="357" /></p>
<p>As you can see it shows two different examples of how to use this command. There were actually lots of examples but the following ones get more and more niche.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Powershell Terminology</strong></h2>
<p>There are several terms you should know in this Powershell for beginners guide. They are not difficult at all but will help so you know what the help system is trying to tell you.</p>
<ul>
<li>Cmdlet</li>
<li>Parameter</li>
<li>Alias</li>
<li>Function</li>
<li>Variable</li>
<li>Module</li>
</ul>
<p>A Cmdlet is the command you will be typing. It has a nice naming convention that will be of the verb-noun format. The verb parts are actions that do something. Example of verbs are import, set, get, and stop. The noun parts are what the verbs act upon. This could be module, process, help, or service.</p>
<p>Parameters customize what a Cmdlet will do. You will see the parameters of a Cmdlet when using the help for it. To use a parameter you will use a dash, a space, the parameter name, another space, and a value.</p>
<p>An Alias is another form of a Cmdlet that you use a lot. It is a shortcut basically. You can make an Alias by the below syntax.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-837 size-large" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-5-1024x527.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 5" width="1024" height="527" /> Powershell For Beginners</p>
<p>You can see from the above command that I made a shortcut to calc.exe and named it just c. So then when I typed c at the prompt my calculator opened. You can do this for any Cmdlet to save you time so make use of it when the need arises.</p>
<p>A Function is a piece of code that is re-usable. If you have any programming experience at all then you are already familiar with this terminology.</p>
<p>Variables are just the same as they are in <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-read-data-from-a-file-with-c/">programming languages</a>. They hold values. It is like an empty box until it has a value.</p>
<p>Modules are a series of commands that are related to other products usually.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Piping Commands</strong></h2>
<p>Powershell, just like other tools, can send the output of one command into another command. This is called piping. In the syntax you do it with a vertical bar just like with Unix. Look at the following example. I have a simple text file on my desktop with some content inside. I am going to run two different commands which are [Get-Content] and [Measure-Object]. However, I am going to do it in one line and pipe the output of [Get-Content] into the [Measure-Object] command so that it can do its magic.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-838 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-6.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 6" width="1093" height="125" /></p>
<p>I used the [Get-Content] Cmdlet or command followed by the path to my text file that I wanted to analyze with [Measure-Object]. I then used a vertical bar to pipe its output into [Measure-Object]. You should also notice that I used the parameters character, line, and word for [Measure-Object]. So pretty interesting for sure. This is just one example of piping Powershell for beginners.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Running Scripts</strong></h2>
<p>What is scripting? Scripting is the automation of tasks. You usually perform a task every time you type out a full working command in Powershell. To get scripting working you will need to set things up first.</p>
<p>By default Powershell is set to only run signed scripts. So to run your own scripts you will need to change this behavior. Run the following command below.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-840 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-7.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 7" width="1083" height="129" /></p>
<p>You will need to run this as an administrator. There are several other execution policies available but this is the one I recommend. You should not use the -unrestricted policy. It is too insecure.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Commenting Code</strong></h2>
<p>You should always comment whatever code or commands you type so that you or others will know exactly what is meant. Systems can break with the wrong commands so comment so that everyone knows exactly what is happening or will happen. To comment you add a # on the line of code that you do not want to execute.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-841 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-8.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 8" width="1068" height="101" /></p>
<p>That's easy enough. Lets move on then.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Variables</strong></h2>
<p>As mentioned above somewhere, a variable is an empty container. It is waiting to hold a value so that it can be used. The data type of a variable can be a string, integer, decimal, or an array. Variables start with the $ symbol. Here is a basic example.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-842 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-9.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 9" width="1064" height="118" /></p>
<p>Yes this is very simple but it shows how the variables work. You can do this from the console , like I just did, or  within a script. It works the same way. You could even pipe that into a text file and email it to your boss so he would know how much money to allocate for new equipment. The [Write] command just writes the output to the screen so you all could see the results.</p>
<p>This is a string variable and I include it because it is done slightly different than a numerical variable. See below.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-843 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-10.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 10" width="1070" height="165" /> Powershell For Beginners</p>
<p>Now we are ready to use that variable any time we want.</p>
<p>If you are working in the console and you want to remove a variable then there are ways to do that.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-846 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-12.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 12" width="1072" height="200" /></p>
<p>You can see that when I sent the <a href="http://aindien.com/beginning-c-input-output-basics/">output</a> to the screen at first the variable $Switches had a value of 2. After I removed the variable there was nothing to write to the screen.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Arrays</strong></h2>
<p>An Array is a container, like a variable, that holds a definable number of values that are of a single type. Every value inside an Array is called an element. They are indexed starting at 0. An Array can hold numerical or string values. Look to my example below to see how to do it.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-845 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-11-1.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 11" width="1066" height="201" /></p>
<p>That should be easy enough to follow. I made two different arrays with data on the types of phones I have and the respective quantities.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Sorting And Filtering</strong></h2>
<p>Sorting and filtering the data that you have will be very important in Powershell for beginners. For example, you may want to do a certain action on only a select few items. You could run a command to find the few that you are looking for and do some action to them. Now you may be thinking this is not a big deal if you have 10 total items in your list and you would be right then. If, however, you have 15,000 items in your list or spreadsheet then you will appreciate being able to do this in five minutes instead of weeks. I will look again at my phone type array and look for anything that starts with "p".</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-847 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-13.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 13" width="1073" height="199" /></p>
<p>Ok that is helpful. My phone list does not have too many in it but if it did this would take the same amount of time.</p>
<p>Lets sort my list of phone brands now. That is easily done and will be quite helpful at some point.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-848 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-14.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 14" width="1071" height="201" /> Powershell For Beginners</p>
<p>That is quick and very useful. As you can see I once again piped the output of my array into the sort command. If you want it to sort in descending order then just add the -descending parameter to sort-object.</p>
<p>You can also sort by length. I am sure this would be useful to someone.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-849 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-15.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 15" width="1071" height="198" /></p>
<p>There we go. It is pretty cool to be able to manipulate data like this. My phone brands are sorted by the length of their name.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Incorporating Logic</strong></h2>
<p>Conditional logic and <a href="http://aindien.com/beginning-c-making-decisions/">decisions</a> can be very important in Powershell for beginners to run scripts correctly. You might have certain conditions you need to be met before you want certain things to run. It could be your whole script or just portions. There are many ways to do this but the most basic is through [if] and [if-else] loops. Here is a short [if] statement.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-851 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-16.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 16" width="1156" height="201" /></p>
<p>You can see I made a variable and called it [$magnets]. The next line is a statement where I test a basic condition. Since the condition passes (magnets = 5), the next part writes "You have enough magnets" to the screen.</p>
<p>Now that is okay but we can do better. Another version of an [if] loop is an [if-else] loop. This will let us deal with the problem if the condition is not met.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-852 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-17.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 17" width="1147" height="200" /> Powershell For Beginners</p>
<p>At first you can see that I had [$magnets] equal to 7 and when I ran the condition loop it passed and my success message appeared on the screen. Then, however, I went back and changed my variable [$magnets] to equal 4 and ran my conditional loop again. Of course it failed and told me to go back and get more magnets. While this is basic it does show you some of the capabilities of basic programming that Powershell is capable of.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Looping</strong></h2>
<p>Looping your <a href="http://aindien.com/essential-linux-commands-to-get-you-started/">commands</a> and part of your scripts is the next topic I want to talk about in this Powershell for beginners guide. If you have been exposed to any programming before then you knew I was going to get here eventually. So what is a loop? Loops are commands or tasks that are repeated until they reach a condition that tells them to stop. So lets do some looping shall we?</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-854 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-18.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 18" width="1149" height="200" /></p>
<p>Alright I admit it, I enjoy playing the Pokemon card game. My son and I play together now after he introduced me to it. These are some of my favorites that I play with and I needed something to put into an array.</p>
<p>We can also do a [for] loop. These are handy when you want to work on certain elements of an array or just run a loop a certain number of times. Here is an example where 0-13 are output to the screen.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-855 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-19.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 19" width="1152" height="224" /> Powershell For Beginners</p>
<p>The [for] loop looks a bit crazy I know if you have not seen them before but they work like a charm. The first part after [for] initializes the $i variable to 0. In the middle section the ending value of the $i variable is given. The last part increments $i step by step. The rest of the line outputs the value of the $i variable one value and step at a time.</p>
<p>Another type of loop is the [while] loop. It can do a lot too. It just depends on what you need of course. Here is an example of counting down while the variable $n does not equal 0.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-856 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-20.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 20" width="839" height="520" /></p>
<p>The last major type of loop is a [Do] loop. This is a handy loop when you need to run through your commands at least once. It allows you to loop while the condition is true or false.  So here is a small [Do] loop where I start my variable $n at 0, then increment for each time the loop runs, prints the value of the variable $n at each loop iteration, until finally the value of the variable $n reaches 10 and the loop exits.</p>
<p><img class="wp-image-858 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/27/Powershell-For-Beginners-21.png" alt="Powershell For Beginners 21" width="837" height="221" /> Powershell For Beginners</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>
<p>This <a href="https://powershell.org/articles/">Powershell</a> for beginners guide is really a small sampling of the basics. There is still a lot to cover and I hope you will go through all of these examples with me. Hopefully once you do that you will be able to come up with your own testing and experiments. That is truly the fun of scripting and programming. Create your own scripts that do something you need to automate. It will be very fun for you and make you more efficient at whatever tasks you need to complete.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Aindien&#x27;s Hints On Using Onenote</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-hints-on-using-onenote.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-hints-on-using-onenote.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote0-1.png" alt="" />
                    <p>In this article I am going to give you some hints on using OneNote from Microsoft Office. OneNote is a great program to keep detailed records, a journal, documentation, or even a simple checklist. It has a lot of uses for a lot of people. Since you can customize the workflow in it almost anyone can make use of it.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote0-1.png" alt="" />
                <p>In this article I am going to give you some hints on using OneNote from Microsoft Office. OneNote is a great program to keep detailed records, a journal, documentation, or even a simple checklist. It has a lot of uses for a lot of people. Since you can customize the workflow in it almost anyone can make use of it.</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Hints On Using OneNote</strong></h2>
<p>I use OneNote every day. I write about products that I enjoy using. Most of us have access to Microsoft Office at work or at home and <a href="https://products.office.com/en-US/onenote">OneNote</a> is included for free with it. It just makes sense to use it to your advantage. So my examples and ideas are how I use it and from my own perspective. I just wanted to mention that before I started.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Use It For Your Documentation</strong></h2>
<p>I document and keep records of a lot of different things. I do it for home and for work. To get started and use it to its full advantage you will want to sign in. Use your Microsoft <a href="http://aindien.com/getting-started-with-windows-10-accounts/">account</a> or set one up if you do not have one. This allows you to sign in wherever you are to get your notebooks. You can set up multiple notebooks all full with tabs or just use one main notebook. You can have as many notebooks as you want or even tabs in a notebook for that matter. It is your preference on that but if you are new to OneNote I would just use one at first. When you have a use for another notebook it is easy to set another one up.</p>
<ul>
<li>To create a new notebook:</li>
<li>Go to top left of screen and click on File</li>
<li>Select New</li>
<li>Under Notebook Name: name it for the project you want it to represent</li>
<li>Then right below that click on the [Create Notebook] button</li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-812 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-OneNote1.png" alt="hints on using OneNote1" width="735" height="262" /></p>
<p>Make sure and save your notebook to the OneDrive account that came with Microsoft Office. This will allow you to access it anywhere.</p>
<p>I have tabs for Powershell, Bash commands, checklists for hard things to remember, lists of ideas for various things, and projects I want to work on. I have many others as well but I won't bore you with everything. The point is that I document things I need to remember or would be helpful to be able to refer to.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Organizing Your Thoughts</strong></h2>
<p>As mentioned slightly before, there are many ways to organize your ideas in your notebook. I have already said that you can have any number of notebooks. Within your notebooks you can have just many sections. Sections are the next logical way to organize your data. They look like tabs on your screen that you can click. They are just to the right of your notebook name. You can make a new section by clicking the [+] sign. You can double click or right click to rename it to whatever you like.</p>
<p>Now within each section you can also have various pages. At the far right and just below your name or the search box there is another part called [+ Add Page]. Click that to add a page to a section.</p>
<p>For each page you can also make a subpage if you want to. To do this just right click your page, assuming you have created one, then select subpage. This is the smallest level of organization that you can do but it should be plenty for most people. Don't feel like you have to do all of this though as you do not. Just do what you need.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Making Notes</strong></h2>
<p>OneNote is a note taking app. That is its main function. You can add content to the section, the page, or the subpage. The content itself can be:</p>
<ul>
<li>Typed notes</li>
<li>Video</li>
<li>Audio recording</li>
<li>Handwriting</li>
<li>Pictures</li>
<li>Files like PDF's</li>
</ul>
<p>One of my favorite hints on using OneNote is that you can drag a PDF you want to refer to straight into a section. You can do the same with pictures or screen shots too. I do this when someone else has given directions on how to do things. Just take a screenshot and put it in there. I have put map sections in there too. Once that is done I can pull this stuff up on any desktop, tablet, or even my phone. That way I don't have to go find it again.</p>
<p>Content and notes are put in containers on each section. This container is just a box that grows with what you do. You can expand it yourself by dragging from the lower right corner and moving it completely by dragging from the top bar of the box.</p>
<p>Formatting your notes is just as easy. At the top as with any Microsoft product they have many options for fonts, colors, and making things look nice. Be creative and play around with it. For most of mine I prefer to add gridlines like college ruled paper has. That is under the [View] option on the menu.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Color Code Your Thoughts</strong></h2>
<p>One of the best hints on using OneNote is to color code sections of text within a tab. Think about what colors you want to use for certain things and do that consistently. If your tabs are long like mine are it will help you find sections and your information much faster. To do this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Select the text that you want to be a different color.</li>
<li>A box will pop up to your right after you let up on your mouse.</li>
<li>There will be a part for [Font Color].</li>
<li>Click the small arrow next to [Font Color].</li>
<li>A huge selection of colors will be shown, just click one of the colors.</li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-813 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote2.png" alt="hints on using onenote2" width="614" height="376" /></p>
<p>Another color tip I just thought of is to color your section tabs and screen color. You can do this by right-clicking on a section tab and choose the color option at the bottom. This is a nice way to organize your pages and sections by type. It makes them just look nicer as well.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Using Tags</strong></h2>
<p>A lot of people use tags in other programs so this is one of the more familiar hints on using OneNote. This is a good way to cross reference your individual sections and notes together. For example I script a lot using Powershell and I have a section just for it. I have added tags to certain types of scripts that I have in there and I can search just for those types of scripts using that tag.</p>
<p>Another example is that I have a section for customer I do work for. I use a tag for each customer. I just use their name. So now when they call me I can just search their name in the tags and see their history of work I have done for them.</p>
<p>To use tags just click [Home] on the menu. There is a large [Tag] section at the top middle of menu. Just to the right of the [Heading] box is the [Tags] box. You will see a list of tags that Microsoft thinks is important. There are small arrows for up and down at the right edge of the box. Click those to scroll through their list of tags. To create your own tags go to bottom of list and select customize to make your own.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-825 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote3.png" alt="hints on using onenote3" width="329" height="153" /></p>
<p>Microsoft has included so many tags in their list that sometimes they are hard to keep up with. A solution to this is that you can make your own tags. You do this by choosing the [Customize Tags] selection. Just call the tag what you want and hit ok. They should now appear at the top of the tag list for you.</p>
<p>You can also delete any tags that you want. When looking at your list you can select one and see a big [x] on the right. Hit the [x] to delete that tag. Do this if you don't like the tags by Microsoft or no longer need one that you created.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Searching For Content</strong></h2>
<p>When you are looking for something you need to search for it. You do this by using the [Search Bar] of course. This is where you search for your tags. The search bar has options though. You should notice a little arrow next to where you type your text at. When you hit that arrow you will see how thorough you want to search for your tags. They are:</p>
<ul>
<li>This section</li>
<li>This section group</li>
<li>This notebook</li>
<li>All notebooks</li>
<li>Set this scope as default</li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-827" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote4.png" alt="hints on using onenote4" width="248" height="203" /></p>
<p>When you hit the arrow select one of those first four options then hit it again and select [Set this scope as default]. That will make it easier on you to find things.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Inserting Content</strong></h2>
<p>Getting content into OneNote is your goal here and this app makes it easy. I have already talked about typing notes but there is so much more. Under the [Insert] menu option there are a lot of ways to add content. The [Screen Clipping] option is one of the more commonly used. It will grab a screen capture and save it right into your notebook section that your on. This is a good way to keep track of things to visit later like a recipe page or that cool website that has a OneNote guide on it!</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-828 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote5.png" alt="hints on using onenote5" width="381" height="554" /></p>
<p>Other good options to use are adding pictures, video, and audio recordings. These are pretty self explanatory. You just click the [Pictures] button, for instance, and select the picture you want to add and it is now there in your page. The other options work the same way. There is no right or wrong way, just do whatever makes sense to you. OneNote can adapt to about anything.</p>
<p>One of the things I do a lot is add the date or time to a lot of my notes. This is in the same section just down the tab some on the right.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Adding Files To Sections</strong></h2>
<p>I mentioned before this is one of my favorite hints on using OneNote. I do this regularly. When I find things I like I will drag it into a section to look at later. I can then modify it, delete it, or even add to it. It just depends on what I think of it after I read it. I put PDF's in it mostly but occasionally a spreadsheet as well. This can be very handy if you ever need it. You can even modify them right from there.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Emailing Sections</strong></h2>
<p>Since this is a Microsoft product it works seamlessly with their other products. A good feature that I like a lot is where you can just email a section to someone else. One of the things I do is keep documentation for difficult installs that take lots of steps. One such installs takes 67 steps to get right. For something like that I definitely want to keep track of the individual steps so I can follow a list when I need to do this.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-829 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/23/hints-on-using-onenote6.png" alt="hints on using onenote6" width="722" height="350" /></p>
<p>Someone else was having trouble getting this installed right because he did not keep a list. So I just went to my [Home] button and on the far right there is a large button that says [Email Page]. You just click this and your email program pops up. Add the email address that you want to send it to and they now have it exactly the way you see it. They can even edit it if they need to so they have their own personal notes on it. This is another of my hints on using OneNote that is easy to do and makes efficient use of your time.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Linking Sections</strong></h2>
<p>Another one of my hints on using OneNote is linking sections that are related. For example, I have two different sections and they are called Powershell and Windows Commands. A lot of those are usable regardless of which tool you use. Some, however, are not though. I put a link at the bottom of each of those sections that goes to the other section. If I don't find the command and its syntax I am looking for in one section then I can click link at the bottom to take me to the other section. This is faster than looking for the tab. If you do this a lot it just makes sense to link related sections.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Doing Math</strong></h2>
<p>You can do some basic arithmetic and <a href="http://aindien.com/aindiens-guide-to-digital-analytics-principles/">data collection</a> within sections. It is very basic though so don't expect much. We are limited to addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division. While it handles decimals fine, algebra seems to be beyond its capabilities. So think and expect basic and you will be fine. Still, this is a note taking app and most do not even have this functionality. This is not meant to be Matlab lol.</p>
<p>You can do equations via the [Insert] menu which is useful for basic equations.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Adding Passwords To Sections</strong></h2>
<p>This is one of those hints on using OneNote you should do if you have anything sensitive on your pages. It is also very easy to do and most other note taking apps do not even have this option. To add a password to a section just right-click the section you want to add security to. Once the menu comes up select [Password Protect This Section]. It will ask you for a password and to confirm it. Close OneNote and re-open it. you will now be asked for a password to see the section. That is a great little feature that more applications should incorporate.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Mobile Usage</strong></h2>
<p>I use the mobile app every day also. Just search [OneNote] from the Android or Apple stores. It looks very similar to the desktop version. When I am away from the office I will often add a quick note, a reminder, or document something for later. It syncs almost automatically back to the desktop version in my office.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>
<p>These hints on using OneNote will hopefully shed some light into this powerful piece of software. It has a good sync service and a nice mobile app you should try as well. They both work very well for me. There are many different ways to use OneNote so don't be afraid to experiment and find your own workflow. This concludes my hints on using OneNote but I have guides on <a href="http://aindien.com/11-clever-tips-for-word-2016/">Word</a> and <a href="http://aindien.com/step-by-step-excel-2016-tutorial/">Excel</a> also if your interested.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Aindien&#x27;s Guide To Digital Analytics Principles</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-guide-to-digital-analytics-principles.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-guide-to-digital-analytics-principles.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/25/digital-analytics-principles0.jpeg" alt="" />
                    <p>Digital analytics principles is all the rage these days. It is easy to understand why. When you have a website you need to know exactly what your visitors are doing. You need to know where they are going and what buttons they are clicking on.This is where Analytics comes in. It is an extremely useful tool but you need to know how to use it. In this article I talk about terms, how to get started, and using it to your website's advantage.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/25/digital-analytics-principles0.jpeg" alt="" />
                <p>Digital analytics principles is all the rage these days. It is easy to understand why. When you have a website you need to know exactly what your visitors are doing. You need to know where they are going and what buttons they are clicking on.This is where Analytics comes in. It is an extremely useful tool but you need to know how to use it. In this article I talk about terms, how to get started, and using it to your website's advantage.</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Digital Analytics Principles</strong></h2>
<p>Digital analytics principles are not hard to learn about but there is not a lot of good information out there. I hope my guide here will fill out some of that missing information about how things are done. This guide on digital analytics principles will be divided up into:</p>
<ul>
<li>Behavioral Analytics - understanding how visitors are interacting with your site.</li>
<li>Metrics - understand the metrics associated with behavioral analytics.</li>
<li>Ways to look at data - discover ways of viewing data in relation to user commonalities and differences.</li>
<li>Using analytics to make decisions - learn how to translate data about your website into action.</li>
</ul>
<p>Analyzing data is key to understanding customers. Doing so in a detailed way allows us to determine what to do with our <a href="http://www.aindien.com">website</a> that will ultimately make more sales.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Identifying the Problem</strong></h2>
<p>For analytics to do us any good we have to understand our problem. The problem could be our traffic or our time on page. It can be many other things as well. Whatever it is we have to understand it and identify it. This will allow us to focus on it so we can look for answers in our data. A definition to a problem like this is often called key performance metrics. It is the data that truly matters.</p>
<p>Once you define your key metrics then you try to break them down into manageable parts that will be included into your data platform.</p>
<p>Our data for this scenario could be customer data collected over the years. It will contain buying habits, trends, and what does not work.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Behavioral Analytics</strong></h2>
<p>Behavioral analytics helps you understand what your visitors do on your site. It is the data that tells you how customers behave on your site. It can show you what element looks interesting to any particular visitor. The analytics can also show you how much they scroll on your pages. The parts of behavioral analytics that are important are :</p>
<ul>
<li>Interactions - this is the number of clicks on any particular page.</li>
<li>Elements - these are hyperlinks, forms, pictures, and text.</li>
<li>Screenshots - this is an image taken by our operating system of the screen.</li>
<li>User exploration - this is where visitors go within your website.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Visitors</strong></h2>
<p>Visitors are the life blood of your website. You need to make them happy so they will be a life long customer.</p>
<ul>
<li>Visits - any specific time a visitor goes to a page on your site.</li>
<li>Page Views - this is the number of times a certain page has been viewed. The time period these views happened within do not matter either.</li>
<li>Unique Visitors - this is calculated with the help of cookies in a visitor's browser.</li>
<li>Bounce rate - this is the rate that visitors visit your website and then leave without going to another page. It may mean something but then it may not.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Traffic</strong></h2>
<p>Analyzing traffic is another key component of analytics. Knowing where it comes from and where it goes after viewing your <a href="http://aindien.com/scaling-network-2016/">website</a> is a good indicator of what is happening on any particular page.</p>
<ul>
<li>Traffic sources - there are various sources of traffic which include direct traffic, search traffic, and referral traffic.</li>
<li>Direct - these are visits when a user types in your address or comes in through a bookmark.</li>
<li>Search engine - search traffic is when users arrive via google, bing, or yahoo.</li>
<li>Referral - this traffic sources comes from links on other sits or social media.</li>
<li>Filters - this modifies the data that you see in order to make it more accurate. Basically they create a subset of the data.</li>
<li>Groups - A group could be a certain area or category of pages within your site.</li>
<li>Exit Pages - These are pages or forms where you direct a customer to leave under certain conditions after they have done something.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Campaigns</strong></h2>
<p>Doing a targeted campaign can be very effective. This is one of the more important digital analytics principles. It is very important because you are targeting people who are already likely to be interested in your site or product. If done wrong, though, it can cost you a lot of money with very little results. No one wants that. This can be accomplished through your URL which can track campaign visits and information.</p>
<ul>
<li>Purpose of Site - it should generate leads for your business, advertise new products, and help customers find information.</li>
<li>Key performance indicators - these metrics or indicators for your business are what you evaluate to see if you are succeeding.</li>
<li>Key metrics - This is what has been identified to be valuable for your site. It could be visitors or time on page for example.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Setting Up Your Analytics</strong></h2>
<p>First of all, you need to know why you have a web site and what you want it to accomplish. This is called setting goals. You need goals so you can actually use the analytics you are examining. Some common reasons why you have a site could be:</p>
<ul>
<li>help customers find information faster.</li>
<li>make sales so your growth increases steadily.</li>
<li>automate tasks that can be done by customers.</li>
<li>keep customers coming back and developing a loyal following.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Obtaining Your Goals</strong></h2>
<p>The first thing you have to do is define your goals. Decide on this explicitly and know when you are getting there. This makes the whole process much easier. Do this by having your key metrics. It always help to get the support of management and peers in this process too. This helps because it will be easier to budget for things when you have the people behind the budgets supporting you. Your budget should account for tools and training specifically. Do your research and get the right tool. No need to buy too expensive at first if your a small company. Create a schedule where you will present the findings and reports. This will let everyone know what the status is and how everyone is doing overall.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Hierarchy Of Goals</strong></h2>
<p>I named this step like this because there are always first steps a customer will do before others. When a customer lands on my site he almost always looks at my most popular articles first before exploring my blog page. Then they might go to my regular blog page. After that if all goes well they will sign up for my newsletter. So you can see there is always a certain order or path that is followed.</p>
<p>For your site, you must identify this behavior and streamline it. Make it easy to do it by making your path stand out. You can even restructure your site to help once you have identified what your visitors will most likely do. Using these digital analytics principles will surely help you in recognizing these goals.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Analyzing The Data</strong></h2>
<p>While there is a lot to take in, there are some basic things to consider.</p>
<ul>
<li>Analyze your metrics that you decided on to make sure your on track.</li>
<li>Organize your data as much as possible and divide it up into segments.</li>
<li>Look at your site and get rid of underperforming pages.</li>
<li>Choose filters for your data that make sense for your business.</li>
</ul>
<p>It is a good idea to compare the number of visitors with the quality of your visitors. Choose your filters carefully and look at each set of data in detail. Analyzing referral traffic versus search traffic can be very helpful to decide where you focus your efforts.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>How To Use Analytics</strong></h2>
<p>There are many ways to use analytics. Every company or organization will find a slightly way in which to analyze their success. Some key ones are:</p>
<ul>
<li>User behavior - this is how customers use your site.</li>
<li>Measuring your goals - this is related to your metrics. Seeing what brings traffic to your site is always helpful.</li>
<li>Conversion rates - this is related to the success of your site. It shows you how many people do what you ask them to do.</li>
<li>Reporting data - after your metrics are defined you can set up a dashboard for easy to see data.</li>
<li>Further improvements - After you identify weak points you can then work to improve them.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h2>
<p>Understanding some basic digital analytics principles are key to knowing your business. Seeing where users click and go to on your site are nice and all but as you can see there is a lot more to it than that. Knowing what happens when a visitor converts and when they do not is just as important. This is all in the data. You first have to define an issue you want to analyze within your site. You then have to see what visitors do first and what they do last. Using a platform that displays what is important to your business is also important. There are many things to consider when analyzing analytics but with some proper planning it can be done.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Getting Started With Windows 10 Accounts</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/getting-started-with-windows-10-accounts.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/getting-started-with-windows-10-accounts.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/26/IMG_20180417_082431-1.jpg" alt="" />
                    <p>Getting started with Windows 10 accounts is easy. There is a lot to Microsoft's new operating system and it changes constantly. It has been out a while now but it seems that the major changes are over for a while. So now is a good time to talk about user accounts.  In this article I will go over the things you need to have a great experience with it.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/26/IMG_20180417_082431-1.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>Getting started with Windows 10 accounts is easy. There is a lot to Microsoft's new operating system and it changes constantly. It has been out a while now but it seems that the major changes are over for a while. So now is a good time to talk about user accounts.  In this article I will go over the things you need to have a great experience with it.</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Getting Started With Windows 10 Accounts</strong></h2>
<p>Many people are worried about having to learn <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_10">Windows 10</a>.  For all the differences you will see, it is still an operating system. When considered from that point of view, it really is not so different after all.</p>
<p>Some things are the same as older Windows operating systems but many others have changed. This is a new Windows. For the most part, it looks and acts differently. I am going to explain as much as I can to help with everything that is different. Windows 10 accounts are no exception either. They are done differently.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>User Accounts</strong></h3>
<p>Everyone that uses a computer has a user account. This could be an administrator, guest, or basic account for yourself. Sometimes multiple people share the same computer. This is when multiple accounts are more important. It is more secure to have multiple accounts if others use the same computer. Your data will stay safe this way.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Logging In</strong></h3>
<p>When you first turn on your computer you will see the login screen. You can select the user, enter a password, or switch users.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Logging Out</strong></h3>
<p>When you want to shut down, restart, or log out there is a quick way. Most people open up the start menu but I recommend something else. It is quicker to right click the start menu (windows button on bottom left) then follow then use mouse to highlight and select the option you want to use. If you just want to sign out then hit the [Windows+L] buttons at the same time.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Sign-In Options</strong></h3>
<p>Getting started with Windows 10 accounts includes several different sign-in options. They are pretty self explanatory so I will just list them so you are aware they exist.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Require sign-in</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Password</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Picture password</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Pin</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Password Policy</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Lock Screen</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Making Strong Passwords</strong></h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">It is very important to have a password or password phrase that is secure. Everyone knows this. Most people do not know how to create strong passwords, however. Here are a few tips.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">It needs to be long(10-15) characters at least</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Uppercase letters</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Use symbols</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Make it a phrase that only makes sense to you</span></li>
</ul>
<p>If someone on your computer forgets their password you can use any administrator account to reset the password for their Windows 10 account.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Types Of Accounts</strong></h3>
<p>There are several different types of Windows 10 accounts. They are:</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Administrator account</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">User accounts with administrator privileges</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Basic accounts</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Guest accounts</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Microsoft accounts</span></li>
</ul>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Administrator Accounts</strong></h4>
<p>The administrator account is a super user. This Windows 10 accounts and the programs you run inside it can do anything. This can be risky if you are not an experienced computer user. For example, if you get some malware then that malware has the same privileges as the account you are running as. That is how the administrator account can be risky. These accounts are used to set up computers for other users.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Administrative User Accounts</strong></h4>
<p>This is a basic user account that has been granted most of the administrator account powers. It is safer to use from a security standpoint. Most users should create one of these.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Basic Accounts</strong></h4>
<p>Basic Windows 10 accounts have just enough privileges to do everyday tasks. This is what most people should use. It will protect you from viruses and other malware. You will not be able to change setting made by an administrator account.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Guest Account</strong></h4>
<p>These are for guests. Specifically, this account is for someone who does not regularly use your computer. They can do basic things like check email or browse the web but that is about it. You do not want guests doing much anyway.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>The Microsoft Account</strong></h4>
<p>These are very nice accounts to have. They can be very flexible. Logging in with a Microsoft account lets you use any computer with Windows 10. You do not have to have a previously created account to use that computer. You can also use software like Office365 and OneDrive much easier. Your settings and files also sync automatically when you use a Microsoft account.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Managing User Accounts</strong></h3>
<p>At home, make sure you have access to an administrator account. Creating one is a straightforward process if you need to. This is useful to control what happens on your computer. Most often you will want to activate some parental controls so your kids do not have access to much. Do not share your administrator password with anyone.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Changing Account Types</strong></h4>
<p>Changing Windows 10 accounts type is easy enough. You can change an account from <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-make-the-jump-to-system-administrator/">administrator</a> to basic and from basic to administrator. This can be useful in some situations.</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Enabling Guest Account</strong></h4>
<p>The guest account is usually disabled by default. Their is not much need for guest accounts so Microsoft does not want to complicate things. Since it is for temporary users it is also easy to enable. You just open the computer management tool and look under Local Users and Groups. It has very few privileges so you do not have to worry about them messing with settings.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Deleting Accounts</strong></h3>
<p>Most accounts can be deleted. Deleting an account will get rid of all the data associated with that account. You will have to weigh the significance of deleting any particular user account. Anyone with administrator access can do this. You will not be able to recover document, pictures, email, or music. Be careful when doing this.</p>
<p>There is an option to save files when you try to delete an account. This should be done if that user has any data in his account.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Using A New Account</strong></h3>
<p>Each account will have its own settings. You can have your separate list of programs, files, and customized features on each individual account. When you start your computer up it will eventually come to the lockscreen. You can hit the spacebar, click your mouse, or even roll your mousewheel to access the sing-in page. This is where you enter your password. Hit the [enter] button or click the arrow next to the sign-in box to log in.</p>
<p>You will have no data yet when you first log in. The desktop and user folders will all be relatively empty. Click the menu to see a list of programs you will have access to. This will include productivity software, browsers, and other tools.</p>
<p>A basic account will often have some restrictions. You might not be able to access everything on the computer or make changes to its functionality.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>User Account Control </strong></h3>
<p>This system is how user accounts are managed in Windows 10 accounts. Many links in the settings or control panel will need administrator access to use. If you click on one of these links it will ask for an administrator password if you are using a basic account. This is a good safety feature. It will prevent users from accidentally changing key components of Windows. It is especially useful in keeping children from doing things they should not.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Creating Reset Disks </strong></h3>
<p>A reset disk can be very useful. It will allow you to access your system if you have forgotten your password. You will need to do this before you forget your password. This disk is typically an USB drive.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Administrator User</strong></h3>
<p>Some programs will want you to have higher privileges for it to work properly. You will need to use this program as an administrator at this point. Right click the app and choose [run as administrator].</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>No Password To Sign In</strong></h3>
<p>This is a bad idea unless the computer is secure in your home and your the only user. You will definitely want this at work or in the public. It is your protection from <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-protect-yourself-from-ransomware/">ransomware</a> and from others. At home it can be an inconvenience for it to lock every 5 minutes when your the only one there. To change this setting:</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Right click on the start menu and choose setting.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Choose the [system] button in the top left of screen.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">On left hand side choose the [power and sleep] option.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Choose to never lock or set a certain time.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Advanced Options</strong></h3>
<p>The advanced options for Windows 10 accounts are in the <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-use-the-computer-management-tools-in-windows-10/">computer management</a> section. Power users and experienced information technology people can use this section to have more control over their computer. To get there you can:</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Right click the start menu.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Left click the [computer management] option.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>Account settings are the [Local Security Policy]. Additional security settings can be adjusted here.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Credential Manager</strong></h3>
<p>This is a good time to talk storing your passwords since we are talking about Windows 10 accounts. This is done by using the credential manager. Access this by searching credential manager from the Windows 10 start menu. This app will submit your credentials for you when you access certain sites or machines. You can enter them manually or wait until Windows asks you for them.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>When different Windows 10 accounts are used the computer feels totally new for each person. Each person can personalize their desktop and the coloring of the system once they are logged in. Having user accounts makes your computer safer. You will need at least one administrator for your computer to control what happens. Everyone should use the most basic account they can to provide least privilege in case accidents happen. Do not forget to make strong passwords and change them occasionally. You will be glad you did.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Aindien&#x27;s Guide To Network Communications</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-guide-to-network-communications.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-guide-to-network-communications.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/24/network_communications.png" alt="" />
                    <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>A computer network can handle a lot of different roles these days. Essentially it pushes data around to devices and controls what happens. Some of the more interesting uses for a network now is VOIP communications and video conferencing. In this guide to network communications I go over some of those details.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/24/network_communications.png" alt="" />
                <p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>A computer network can handle a lot of different roles these days. Essentially it pushes data around to devices and controls what happens. Some of the more interesting uses for a network now is VOIP communications and video conferencing. In this guide to network communications I go over some of those details.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<h2 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Guide To Network Communications</strong></h2>
<p>First of all, the network communications in a business or organization can take on many forms. A business or individual may use part or even all of these types of communications. In conclusion, they each have their use cases and advantages.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Voice over IP.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Video broadcasts.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Surveillance.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Collaboration software.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Quality of Service.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-697 size-large" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/24/network_communications3-1024x410.png" alt="network_communications" width="1024" height="410" /></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Voice over IP</strong></h3>
<p>Voice over IP is used in many if not most business environments today. You can get a lot of cool features with these types of phones and save a ton of money over traditional phone services. Another reason this has become so popular is because it uses the same Ethernet cabling as the rest of our network.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Video Broadcasts</strong></h3>
<p>Video of most varieties can also travel over the network, so others can see it. This can be a streaming event like a webinar or just something made locally by a department that needs to be seen by the entire organization.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Surveillance</strong></h3>
<p>Surveillance and security cameras are also part of this. They may not get sent out as videos very often but the footage sometimes needs to be seen. Among your typical network communications this is often the most important but also the least used.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Collaboration Software</strong></h3>
<p>Another nice advantage of network services is collaboration software. This can be something that helps with documents or even some sort of chat software like Cisco stuff or Slack.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Quality of Service</strong></h3>
<p>Quality of service is essentially several mechanisms working together to guarantee delivery of time sensitive packets. This is important because too much data loss with one of the previously mentioned services will cause it not to work. Furthermore, we need a quality of service that is at least to a certain point so we can do our work.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Data can be classified by address or application type.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Once it is classified it can be prioritized by the traffic type that works for your business.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">For example we can make voice traffic a higher priority than other types of traffic.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Virtualization</strong></h3>
<p>Virtualization allows you to connect virtual machines and devices to a network in the same way that you connect physical devices. You can connect these virtual machines without using a physical network adapter. Consequently, this is becoming one of the most important types of network communications as it is becoming central to all that we do.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This makes it easy to build a complex network.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">No need to invest in a large amount of expensive physical hardware.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This model supports a high number of virtual networks on just one physical network adapter.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">These networks and network devices will use our current DHCP server.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>Virtual machines connect to a network through a computer with a network adapter. It can connect to all computers connected to that network adapter. Without using a network adapter it exists as part of an internal virtual machine network. This process does require virtual components to function which acts in a similar way to their physical counterparts in a physical network.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Virtualization Devices</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://aindien.com/networking-basics-applications-network-devices/">Virtual Switch</a></li>
</ul>
<p>A virtual switch allows you to connect virtual servers to separate lans. Since they behave the same as a physical switch a virtual switch allows you to separate traffic for security and quality of service reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://aindien.com/computer-networking-networking-hardware/">Virtual router</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This virtual device will also allow you to route traffic between <a href="http://aindien.com/computer-networking-devices/">devices</a> just as a real firewall would.</p>
<ul>
<li>Virtual firewall</li>
</ul>
<p>These filter packets and monitor traffic.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Storage Area Network</strong></h3>
<p>This is any high performance network whose primary purpose is to enable storage devices to communicate with computer systems and with each other. This gives us fault tolerance and redundancy with our storage.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Storage devices provide access to shared block level data storage.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This is used to make storage devices accessible to servers so that the operating system sees them as locally attached devices.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">The server accesses the storage at the block level.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">The storage appears locally attached like an internal disk.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;">Fiber Channel</h3>
<p>Fiber channel is often used as the network communications protocol in a storage area network. A storage area network is often made up of multiple fiber channel switches.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Attached Storage</strong></h3>
<p>This is a file level data storage device. It will not appear as a local storage device.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">It attaches directly to a network much like computers and servers.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Provides data access and file storage to computer systems on the network.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Effectively replaces one or more file servers by providing the central storage locations for users data.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Accessing data storage from network attached storage is done over the IP network using file level protocols.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">The operating system level of the computers and servers do not appear to have the data storage available locally.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Users have to access data as a file share over the network.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Creating file shares on the network attached storage devices enables other computer systems to connect to the shares.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Cloud Computing</strong></h3>
<p>Cloud computing provides access to network communications resources such as services, applications, servers, network infrastructure, and storage on a distributed network. Therefore, this is all on the internet and is basically someone else's resources.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Users access these resources by networking and various internet protocols.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">There are several service models we use in cloud computing and each has their advantages.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) is physical devices.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Platform as a Service (PaaS).</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Software as a Service (SaaS) include any kind of application.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">the hosting provider owns all of this physical infrastructure and rents it to you.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Infrastructure as a Service</strong></h3>
<p>Infrastructure as a Service is talking about your physical devices. It is the lowest <a href="http://aindien.com/how-the-osi-model-works/">level</a> of the network communications. This can be routers, switches, computers, printers, storage devices, power units, racks, locks on doors, and cooling. You can see there is a lot to it. All of this is essential though.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-695 size-large" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/24/network_communications1-1024x455.png" alt="network communications" width="1024" height="455" /></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This infrastructure can replace aging units in your office.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">You can have a separate site that is a backup in case your main office goes down.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This can also fulfill a temporary need for resource expansion.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">It can help you spread out in other geographical areas.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">You can use infrastructure to help with increased loads to a server.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">If you have a short lived project you can rent infrastructure to help and give you more computing power.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Platform as a Service</strong></h3>
<p>Platform as a Service sits just on top of the infrastructure. This usually deals with virtualization and the operating system layer. A platform can be Windows, Linux or BSD. Virtualization refers to a type a hypervisor such as VMWare, Hyper-v, KVM, or Xen.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">The cloud provider is the owner of the platform and as a customer can make use of it.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">The cloud provider manages the installation of the operating system and the hypervisor.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">It can be used for temporary acces to the physical infrastructure and operating system.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">If you do not have the skills to use KVM for example you can let a provider manage this for you.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">You can also rent this if you have a general lack of maintenance skills.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">It can help with development and testing if you do not have the resources in house to do it.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This gives you access to that infrastructure that runs it and also gives you a backup for your running applications.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Software as a Service</strong></h3>
<p>Software as a Service is the top layer of the overall cloud infrastructure. This functionality offers complete applications to the cloud user. A good example of this that most people use is hosted email.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">More examples include web applications, file sharing, business applications, and music services.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">The cloud provider proves access and maintenance to the application.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">We can use this when we want to avoid application and software maintenance tasks.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Another time is when we have outdated software and not enough money to buy new licenses.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">We can use software as a service if we lack the skills to support the existing applications.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">It allows us to focus on the business side of things without hiring an IT department.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Costs can be greatly reduced by using software as a service because we do not have to have all the infrastructure and people to run it.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This is also useful to help with testing applications.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Cloud Deployment Models</strong></h3>
<p>There are different deployment models for cloud computing and hence each describes a way that cloud infrastructure is deployed privately or to the public.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Public cloud computing.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Private cloud computing.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Hybrid cloud computing.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Community cloud computing.</span></li>
</ul>
<p><img class="aligncenter wp-image-696 size-full" src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/24/network_communications2.png" alt="network communications" width="1013" height="714" /></p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Public Cloud Computing</strong></h3>
<p>This will be hosted off site. It is owned by a third party company that sells cloud services to the public in a multi tenant fashion. This means they will have many customers for their services.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">This is usually available to all members of the public or large groups within an industry.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Private Cloud Computing</strong></h3>
<p>This is typically built to be used within an organization. It will most often be developed and run by the organization's IT department, however, it could also be held off site and run by a third party.  A business might develop a private cloud offering in another geographic location so that its employees there have the same resources.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Hybrid Cloud Computing</strong></h3>
<p>This is just a combination of different types. A business would do this if a particular combination fit their business model better. These different cloud models will maintain their own characteristics but are bound together to form a single unit.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">They can also offer standardized access to data and applications.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">A business in the process of converting to cloud computing might use a hybrid cloud while they transition from traditional storage to cloud based storage.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Community Cloud Computing</strong></h3>
<p>A community cloud model is an open inter-network that enables clients to find resources on demand. This is important because it separates an organization from cloud resource providers. There are usually no contracts or agreements that are needed before clients can access the content they require.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Basic Network Requirements</strong></h3>
<p>To implement all of the previously mentioned communication types there are a few basic requirements that you need. I want to go over those now. Most basic networks need centralized network components like a router and a switch. There are others too that you need to make use of typical network communications. As a result, there are many kinds of devices and ideas to consider.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Computers, laptops, tablets, cell phones, and printers.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Routers, switches, and firewalls.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">VOIP phones, network storage, and access points.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Requirements To Consider</strong></h3>
<p>First, it helps if you have an idea of the number of computers, switches, and access points you will have on your network. Consequently, you will want to make sure your devices are large enough for your current needs plus any future <a href="http://aindien.com/scaling-network-2016/">growth</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Internet connectivity - How much bandwidth do you need?</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Wireless connections - You will want a sufficient number of these if you choose to allow wireless at all.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Connectivity of peripherals - Consider how many and where these will be connected.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Access point locations - having good signal is important with the number of laptops,cell phones, and tablets that users bring to work these days.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Network Compatibility</strong></h3>
<p>Not everyone will have the latest technology so we need to make sure they can use our network and resources. We typically do not have to worry about Ethernet because those network interfaces have some built in backwards compatibility. Therefore, if you have multiple locations then you need to have your routers be able to work with each other.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>WiFi Compatibility</strong></h3>
<p>The current wireless interfaces are 802.11ac and 802.11n but they will also support older wireless standards as well. So it is nice that a lot of hardware has built in backwards compatibility. You should still try to plan for using current standards if at all possible though.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Environmental Requirements</strong></h3>
<p>Sometimes our network and its equipment is affected by the environment. Electromagnetic interference is one of the things that can affect our network's performance. An example is our Ethernet cables can be affected by lights in our building. That is the environment lowering our performance. Another example is power cables can cause interference if they are run too closely to the Ethernet cables. Wireless interference is also something you need to pay attention to. There are lots of different kinds of wireless devices and some will certainly affect the performance of your network.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Security Requirements</strong></h3>
<p>Security is a very important topic. When setting up your network communications devices you will want to use private IP addresses inside your network. Use the public Ip address at your edge router so it can do its job.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Make sure you use a firewall.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Use <a style="color: #339966;" href="http://aindien.com/how-to-protect-yourself-from-ransomware/">antivirus and antimalware</a> to protect yourself or your business.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Have firewall software on your servers and clients.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Use good physical security such as key-pad locks on the doors to your network closets.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #339966;">Access to networking equipment should be limited.</span></li>
</ul>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>In conclusion, network communications encompass a large area in Information Technology and networking in general. There are many things to consider when you decide upon a certain communications standard or technology. Even among any particular communication protocol you will see that there are multiple sides to it.</p>
<p>Please leave a comment below to let me know how you liked this article or if you had any questions.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Aindien&#x27;s Elementary Guide To Evernote</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-elementary-guide-to-evernote.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/aindiens-elementary-guide-to-evernote.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How To Use Raid On Your Computer</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jason Moore</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/how-to-use-raid-on-your-computer.html"/>
        <id>https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/how-to-use-raid-on-your-computer.html</id>

        <updated>2019-11-28T14:00:37-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/22/how-to-use-raid-in-your-computer-0.png" alt="" />
                    <p>How to use Raid on your computer is a guide explaining what Raid is and how you should approach it. I talk about how to get started with it and descriptions of the various types. It can be a tough decision as to whether you should use as hardware controller or software but I talk about this as well.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jahlelin.github.io/aindien/media/posts/22/how-to-use-raid-in-your-computer-0.png" alt="" />
                <p>How to use Raid on your computer is a guide explaining what Raid is and how you should approach it. I talk about how to get started with it and descriptions of the various types. It can be a tough decision as to whether you should use as hardware controller or software but I talk about this as well.</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2><strong>How To Use Raid On Your Computer</strong></h2>
<p>Raid, which stands for "redundant array of independent disks", is a way to combine identical types of drives to gain more performance and reliability. It will make them into one large logical drive. You will want to buy the same size drives from the same manufacturer to make things easier and to ensure you have as few issues as possible.</p>
<p>Raid is becoming more popular these days among consumers. It used to only be in the monetary and technical reach of businesses. Now, however, anyone with a newer computer can implement it in the system.  Using Raid storage for your computer can be very helpful. It can do a variety of things such as giving you better performance and and making your data more reliable.</p>
<p>There are many types of Raid and each version offers advantages and drawbacks. It will depend on your situation as to which one makes the most sense for you. It will be different if you use this for your home computer versus in a business somewhere.</p>
<p>There are also more Raid levels than I am listing here but these are the most popular.</p>
<h3><strong>Getting Started With Raid</strong></h3>
<p>The first thing I want to mention is that for the average user I recommend starting Raid with a new system. The reason why is that it will take existing data out of the equation. There are exceptions to this and is if you have an IT professional doing it for you. You will need to image your computer and backup your files before you start this.</p>
<p>A professional will know this and you will be fine like that. I would not recommend an average user to do this unless they have done it several times before. So unless you have an IT professional around or are willing to pay one then start Raid with a new system so there is no chance of you losing anything important.</p>
<h3><strong>Reading and Writing</strong></h3>
<p>Performance in a system consists of reading and writing to your storage. Data speed is often measured in something called IOPS which is input/output operations per second. This is measured in reading IOPS and writing IOPS as well. Get a cache if at all possible as it will help accessing your storage quite a bit.</p>
<p>Raid will add a heavy strain to your CPU so make sure you have a big enough CPU for what you are trying to do or it will become a bottleneck and Raid will not help that much.</p>
<h3><strong>Raid Levels</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #008000;"> 0</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #008000;"> 1</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #008000;"> 5</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #008000;"> 6</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #008000;"> 10</span></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Raid 0</strong></h4>
<p>This type of Raid is just about pure performance. There will be a noticeable increase in how fast your computer seems. The downside is that there is no redundancy in your data. This means that if a disk goes down all of your data will be lost. So why and how  do people use this? You have to have a good backup system in place so that if a disk fails you will be able to recover quickly.</p>
<p>The next thing is you need to store your data on a network resource to mitigate any losses. This means storing your Excel documents on network storage or something like Google Drive or Dropbox. If you do that then you have lost nothing you have created if a disk fails.</p>
<p>The last thing you will want to do is have an imaging system set up of your operating system and installed programs. This type of setup will make an exact copy of your computer and programs that are installed on it. This is how you use it on your computer and enjoy its benefits.</p>
<h4><strong>Raid 1</strong></h4>
<p>This is ideal when you must not lose the data and it will be cheaper than other Raid levels which require more disks. The performance is no better than just using a single drive though so remember that. Data is mirrored across two drives so if one drive fails then data is just copied over from the remaining disk.</p>
<p>The main problem with this is that you only get half the storage of your disks. So, for example, if you use two 1 Tb drives then your total capacity of your array is 1 Tb.</p>
<h4><strong>Raid 5</strong></h4>
<p>This level of Raid is more complex and harder to work with. It requires at least three drives to make it happen but that means the array can withstand a single failed drive and still keep your data intact. Your data is spread across these three drives. Performance is decent here because of the three drives.</p>
<p>Reading data will be pretty fast but writing data will be at a normal one drive rate. Still it is not bad overall though. One of the downsides is that when a drive fails it can take a long time to rebuild it. Your storage capacity will be 2/3 of your total storage and that is not a bad trade off.</p>
<h4><strong>Raid 6</strong></h4>
<p>In a lot of cases this will be superior to the previous version above because of the extra durability of the array. It is more durable because it can withstand two drives failing at exactly the same time and still keep your data intact. That is pretty secure as that will probably never happen to you. Reading data is again quite fast but writing data to disk will be slower.</p>
<p>This is really not much of an issue anymore with modern fast computers. If a drive fails then it takes a long time to rebuild the array and get everything working normally. A system with this enabled works pretty good as a storage server where files have to be retrieved regularly. It is very reliable and pretty fast too. The main downside is it requires four drives but for a business this is not an issue.</p>
<h4><strong>Raid 10</strong></h4>
<p>This is my favorite so let me tell you why. This is a combination of 0 and 1 and it gives you the benefits of both of those levels. If a disk fails then it will be rebuilt quickly and you still have all of your data. Data is spread across all four drives with half on two drives and other remaining data on the other two drives.</p>
<p>This will make it fast and resemble a 0. Your data is also mirrored as in a 1 and that will give it the reliability you need. You will have the best of performance and reliability in your system now.</p>
<p>So what is the drawback? That will be the amount of storage you will have access to. You will only get half the storage that you put into your system and that can worry people sometimes. Remember, however, that storage is cheap and only getting cheaper. Regular hard drives are extremely cheap now for 1 Tb and 2 Tb versions. Depending on your needs this could be a good fit for the average user.</p>
<p>It does get expensive if you are using SSD drives however. They are coming down in price but to a lot of people buying four of them is too much of a cost. It is getting better and that makes it an option worth considering at least.</p>
<h3><strong>Nested Raid Levels</strong></h3>
<p>There are more complex levels of Raid such as 50 or 60. These levels are just combinations of the more basic levels of Raid. They use more drives too and it is not uncommon to use something like twelve drives for one of these configurations.</p>
<h3><strong>Raid Versions</strong></h3>
<p>There is software Raid and hardware Raid. Software Raid is when it is implemented and controlled by your operating system. Windows and Linux flavors both do this and the quality is decent. Hardware Raid uses a separate controller board that plugs into your motherboard like a video card does. Hardware controllers are more expensive but usually offer better performance, features, and reliability.</p>
<h4><strong>Software Raid</strong></h4>
<p>This will be the cheapest way to go about using Raid once you have your disks. Most motherboards and operating systems support and offer it as an easy version. It is free to use and rather easy too.</p>
<ul>
<li><span style="color: #008000;">If your desktop is Windows based then buy a hardware controller board.</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #008000;">Linux desktops have a great version built into their operating system.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>The first step here is to enable Raid in your system's BIOS. It should be an easy to spot option.</p>
<p>Using software Raid will use your system's resources but this should not be an issue if you have the right hardware.</p>
<h4><strong>Hardware Raid</strong></h4>
<p>This involves buying a hardware controller and attaching it to your motherboard and then connecting your drives correctly. Processors on these cards will be smaller and not as powerful as the ones on your motherboard. They can be cheap but I would not buy a cheap one. I would just use software Raid over a cheap controller.</p>
<p>They can also get expensive if you get reliable ones with a large cache built in. I would recommend getting one with a cache as it will improve things a lot.</p>
<h3>Backing Up Your Data</h3>
<p>Before you do anything with your disks it is vital that you have all your data backed up if this is a working system. You will lose any data once you start building your new Raid system. Use some imaging software to take the current state of your PC and save it. Make sure and get all the files in your libraries.</p>
<h3><strong>Raid Should Not Be Your Backup</strong></h3>
<p>At first glance all this talk of mirroring your data makes it seem that this would be a good backup option. That would be incorrect though. Do not try to use this as a backup option. Raid is designed to protect your data from hardware failure. What happens if your operating system or some application becomes corrupt?</p>
<p>That corrupt data is then sent to to your drives and then everything is corrupt. That is why you need to backup your data the regular way too.</p>
<h3><strong>Raid Does Not Stop Viruses and Malware</strong></h3>
<p>Getting a virus or <a href="http://aindien.com/how-to-protect-yourself-from-ransomware/">malware</a> does not crash your hard drive so Raid will not protect your system from these types of failures. Only good antivirus will help prevent this and of course good backups.</p>
<h3><strong>Who Should Use Raid</strong></h3>
<p>Raid is not for everyone as it is more complex and more expensive. The average user will really just need a good SSd and perhaps some extra memory to make their system seem like its new. For the heavy users, however, Raid can be a life saver. Heavy users are those working in large files often. Large video files or raw picture data will often need the boost and reliability of a Raid system.</p>
<h3><strong>Installing The Raid Card</strong></h3>
<p>After you have bought a Raid controller now is the time to install it. You will plug it in just like any normal expansion card. As always make sure to have your whole computer unplugged. If you are not comfortable doing this then please get help. You will usually set up things in your BIOS as your computer boots up.</p>
<h3>Building Your Array</h3>
<p>Once you have your BIOS set the Raid software will build your array. This will take some time and will depend on your version of Raid, how many drives you have, and how much total storage there is in the array.</p>
<h3><strong>Software Time</strong></h3>
<p>It is time for your operating system or hypervisor now. This will depend on how you set your system up but it is the next step.</p>
<h3><strong>Conclusion</strong></h3>
<p>The whole point to use raid on your computer is to make your data more reliable, let your system run faster, or both. How and to what extent that you do so will depend on your situation and your technical expertise. It takes at least two drives and can use many more in your PC so it will be more expensive.</p>
<p>When backing up your PC if there is not something that you know how to do then you need to ask. You can leave a comment here or hire someone as either would be easy and relatively quick with someone that knows what they are doing.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
